Were you always for Donald Trump or did
something change? Because for now, for
from my perspective right now, it seems
like you're thinking he he's the best
option for the country right now. Yes. I
was actually a supporter of Gary
Johnson's um when Donald Trump first
ran. Um, you know, I
I Ronald Reagan was right when he said
that government is the problem. It's not
the solution to the problem. And Gary
Johnson, the former Republican governor
of New Mexico, was the Libertarian
Party's nominee for president twice. So,
I I campaigned in 12 states with Gary. I
introduced him at all of his campaign
stops. Um, I knew that he wasn't going
to win. He did really great by
libertarian standards. He got three and
a half percent. Yeah. Um but it took me
it took me a while before I I moved over
to to Donald Trump. But I'm going to add
though that this is not the Donald Trump
of the first term. Yes, this is a
completely and totally different Donald
Trump. This is a Donald Trump who's far
more
worldly and um who has a deeper
understanding of international events
and much much more willingness to stand
up to the Israelis. I have to say I am
very pleasantly surprised by the way
things have been going since January the
20th.
Okay. Interesting. I I just I was
picking up on that and uh thought I
thought I would ask. You were in the CIA
at the time that that happened and did I
did I think I read online you were at
CIA headquarters when the news came in.
What what were things like
uh with top government leadership? I I
mean I I was in the Dominican Republic
on a Christian mission when it happened.
So I you know I missed out on a lot of
that. Uh but what what was it like at
CIA headquarters and in the country at
that time? Oh
man, that morning I had a meeting
scheduled along with the director of the
CIA's counterterrorism center. We were
going to see Condisa Rice on an issue
that is just so silly
now after 25 years that you would just
shake your head. So, I got a call that
our car was ready and I walked over to
Kofheer Black's office and
um and his
secretary, this this was back in the day
when you couldn't watch TV on your
computer. So, she had a little TV on her
desk and one of the towers of the World
Trade Center was burning. And I said,
"What happened to the World Trade
Center?" And she said, "A plane flew
into it." This is conda rice. No, no,
no. This is cover for black secretary
before we before we drove to the White
House to see condandy Rice. So I said
because I'm an idiot. I said um I said
you know that happened once before 1932.
A plane flew into the Empire State
Building but it was really foggy and
rainy and like it's so crystal clear
today. How can you not see that you're
flying into the World Trade Center? And
as soon as the words came out of my
mouth the second plane flew in. And
neither one of us reacted. And then
finally she turned to me and she said,
"Did you see that or did I imagine it?"
And I ran back to my office. I said,
"Guys, two planes just hit both towers
of the World Trade Center. I think we're
under
attack. I will interrupt myself here and
tell you that two months earlier on July
the 6th, totally normal day, I was
entertaining a group of Middle Eastern
intelligence officers. This is something
we did every single day at the CIA. You
bring them in, you do a day of
briefings, you exchange gifts, you take
them up to get a photo with a with the
director, and then you take them out to
a fancy dinner at night. And then the
next day, you do it with another
country's intelligence service day after
day after day. So on January 6, oh
sorry, uh, uh, July 6th,
2001, I had scheduled this day of
briefings and it was six guys at the
major and lieutenant colonel
level. So I asked the juniormost analyst
on al-Qaeda to come in and just give an
overview of al-Qaeda. But instead of
this junior analyst coming in, Kofheer
Black himself came in with the chief of
operations for Alex Station, the Osama
bin Laden group. And I I jumped up and I
said, "Oh, gentlemen." I said, "This
this is this is Ambassador Kofer Black.
He's the director of the CIA's
counterterrorism center and and this is
the chief of operations for uh the Osama
bin Laden unit." Kofheer sat down and he
said, and this is how he started. He
said, "Something terrible is going to
happen. We don't know exactly what or
where, but it's going to be an attack on
a scale that we've never seen." He said,
"We're hearing al-Qaeda camp commanders
on the phone with their students, and
they're crying and saying, "I'll see you
in paradise. We're hearing code words
for a massive attack. The honey salesman
is coming with vast quantities of honey.
There's going to be a massive wedding.
there's going to be a great football
match, all code for an attack. He said,
"I'm begging you, if you have any
sources inside al-Qaeda, please help
us." And they just sat there and looked
at him. So, at the end of the day, I
sent them back to their hotel, told them
I'll pick them up in a couple of hours
to go to dinner. But I went back to
Kofheer's um office to thank him and I
said, ' Kofer, I I got to ask
you, was that just for their benefit or
were you serious? And he said, "Oh no,
I'm deadly serious. Something terrible
is going to happen." And then September
11th, my first thought was, "This is
what he was he was talking about. This
is what he was warning us about." So the
second plane
hits
and then the third plane goes into the
Pentagon. There were about 300 people in
the office. We all packed up to the
front where Kofheer's office was. You
have to picture an enormous room like a
hotel ballroom with private offices all
around the perimeter and then cubicles,
hundreds of us in cubicles, you know, uh
in the in the center. And there were TVs
hanging down from the ceiling. So you
had CNN and Fox and MSNBC and BBC and RT
and Canel Plus and from all over the
world. We're all watching this as it's
unfolding. Silence. And finally,
somebody behind me shouts, "Will
somebody please
lead?" And it was like somebody had
shaken Coher and he said, "Yeah, you go
to the director's office and tell him
this. You go to security. You go to
operations." Finally, a CIA cop comes
in. The CIA has its own police force.
Um, he came in and said, "Everybody
evacuate." Nobody
budged. So, we're standing there
watching this and then Kofheer pulls out
a chair and stands on a on the chair and
he
says, I'll never forget this. He said,
"Today we're at
war and all of us are going to have to
fight and not all of us are going to
come home.
if this is not for you, no one will
think less of you if you walk out the
door right now. Nobody
budged. Everybody volunteered to go to
Afghanistan because we all knew what
this was. We had been waiting for it. Uh
and then finally the cop came back in
and said, "If you don't evacuate, you'll
be
arrested." So, we evacuate. Took me two
hours just to get out of the parking
lot. I got about halfway to my
apartment. I lived
about six miles from CIA headquarters
and I had to abandon my car on the
George Washington Parkway. My girlfriend
was several floors above me. She later
became my wife. Um so I called her. I
said, "We're evacuating." She said,
"Yeah, I'm leaving right now." I said,
"Meet me at my place." So I abandoned my
car. I walked the last three miles. I
saw the deputy national security adviser
coming across the Teddy Roosevelt bridge
with no
shoes. If you This is how the level of
chaos in Washington that day. He had no
shoes. And I remember saying, "Oh my
god, if the White House is
evacuating, who's leading us?" So we
went to my apartment, we went to the
roof, and we watched the Pentagon burn
for a while. And finally, I said, "This
is ridiculous. we got to go back to
work. And we walked back to my car. I
drove across the grassy median, went
back to CIA headquarters, and I didn't
leave for the next four days. Just
baldled up my jacket and slept under the
desk and slept two hours at a time.
Everybody did that. And then got to, you
know, the theater as quickly as I could.
Wow.
total totally caught off guard. Uh they
knew something big was happening. They
But they you know what, Stephen? They
didn't think it was going to be here.
The conventional wisdom was they're
going to they're going to take out
another embassy, right? They'll probably
do it in the middle of the workday.
Yeah. A big embassy. Paris, London,
Manila, you know, something big. We
didn't think they're going to attack us
right here in the country.
Yeah. Yeah. Wow. Okay. That's
interesting. Um I wanted Yeah, I wanted
to get your uh your insight on that. Um
another question I have kind of related
to this is uh President Trump and Marco
Rubio. They're they're they're talking
about supporting this new leader in
Syria, not fully trusting him, but not
really having anyone else to work with
to avoid ISIS and al Qaeda uh getting
getting big again. What What are your
thoughts on this? Because there's been a
lot of people, oh, look at Trump now
dealing with terrorists and on the other
side they're like, well, he has to to
avoid the worst terrorists. Exactly.
Okay, you're right. And we should call a
spade a spade here. This guy was an
al-Qaeda leader. He was the number two
in
ISIS. Uh he broke off from ISIS,
claiming at the time he wanted to
moderate. The CIA supported um
al-Qaeda in Syria. The State Department
supported the the Kurds and the Defense
Department supported an independent
rebel group.
So, we had the most screwed up policy on
Syria that was
possible.
Um, but you're right, you know, wouldn't
it be lovely if we could just choose the
people that we wanted to lead each
country, but that's just not real life.
Compare it to this. We could have
cultivated a relationship with Fidel
Castro in the 1950s when he was a rebel
leader, and we didn't. Fidel Castro was
a minor league pitcher for the
Washington Senators. He liked the United
States. We could have cultivated that
relationship, but we decided not to
because we had thrown our weight behind
Batista. You know, love him or hate
him. This time it's different. And I
have to say, Donald Trump is playing it
right. We don't have any choice. And
we're not doing this alone. Emanuel
Mcronone, the president of France, has
come out like and laid out the red
carpet and invited Golani to uh to Paris
and then Kier Starmer invited him to
London. So, we're not just we're not
just winging it here. There's been a
there's been a a policy hatched
by by, you know, the allies that we're
going to get it right this time. It took
us a long time to get rid of the Assads
and so we're going to we're going to do
it right this time. And
Golani seems to be playing ball so far.
So one of the most important lessons I
learned in the fight against
al-Qaeda, let me let me rephrase that.
And this is why I I think this policy is
going to work in Syria.
Every al-Qaeda fighter at the grunt
level, at that, you know, 18 and 19 year
old fighter level told exactly the same
story. They were from some isolated
village in whatever country they came
from. They were illiterate. They had no
job skills, no job training, and they
wanted to get married. But what man
would want his wife to marry a kid who
can't read, can't write, and can't work?
Nobody wants their daughter to marry a
guy like that. So the local imam went to
these kids and said, "Why are you here
in this village? You should make
something of yourself. You should go to
Afghanistan and make jihad against the
Americans. And if you do, we'll give you
$300 a month. And if you're martyed,
we'll give your parents a $500 martyrdom
bonus." And they said, "Okay, I got
nothing else going on." They couldn't
find the United States on a map. they
had no beef with the United States, it's
that they were
poor. So, I've always
said if if we were serious, not just the
United States, but the West, were
serious about addressing the root causes
of
terrorism, we would be involved in
widescale economic development and
education. What's the first thing Donald
Trump did in Syria? The very first thing
he lifted
sanctions, he lifted sanctions so now
Syria can accept investment
money. And investment money is going to
build infrastructure, including better
roads, which make trade easier,
especially with Turkey, which is the the
big, you know, 800 pound gorilla on the
block. Um, an
upgrade and the port of
Latakia, right? So ships can come in and
make trade easier. It's building the
economy. Mark my words, in 20 years
there will be no no such thing as a
Syrian terrorist because that economy is
going to be on track. So it may not look
pretty right now, but this was the right
thing to do. Okay. Yeah. I kind of I
kind of
figured that it may not be the per It's
like in Batman. It's not the It's not
the hero you want the but the one that
you need right now. Like we're not
saying the guy's a great guy, but like
it's what we have to work with
right now if we want the area um to to
be better. Uh this has been a this has
been a great discussion. I definitely
want to have you on. I've got uh several
more questions that I could go on and on
and on about. Um, but John, if people
want to follow you online, uh, continue
to hear your your thoughts and
perspectives, where can I point them?
Thank you. Thank you. Everything I I
write and do, I put on Substack. So,
it's, uh,
johnkuryaku.substack.com. I'm on X, uh,
John Kuryaku. I'm on Facebook and I'm on
LinkedIn and Instagram. I've got a TV
show uh on an online platform called CIA
Declassified where we take declassified
documents and tell historical stories
based on the documents. That's at
unified television
unifyd. Uh but everything ends up on
Substack. Well, I'm going to put those
direct links down low uh below, John, so
that people can find your book, your
Substack, and uh your ex. Thank you so
much for coming on. I hope you have a
great rest of your day. Thanks so much.
Same to you. Take care.